{"tossups": [{"question": "This politician called Russia \u201ca riddle, wrapped up in a mystery, inside an enigma.\u201d The failure of the Gallipoli Campaign tarnished the early career of this orator who capped off his best  speeches with phrases like \u201cblood, toil, tears, and sweat\u201d and \u201cthis was their finest hour.\u201d Taking office after Neville Chamberlain resigned, this politician led his country through the Battle of Britain. For 10 points, name this Prime Minister who led Britain through most of World War II.", "answer": "Winston <b><u>Churchill</u></b> [or Sir Winston Leonard Spencer-<b><u>Churchill</u></b>]  [Matt Bollinger]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Before this event, Robert Ricks likely saved many lives by warning that an area would become \u201cuninhabitable for weeks.\u201d The Gretna [GRET-nuh] City police forcibly expelled survivors of this event seeking help and after it, FEMA chief Michael Brown was criticized for his agency\u2019s inaction. Some survivors from this event were relocated to the Astrodome when the Superdome became overcrowded. For 10 points, name this hurricane that nearly destroyed New Orleans.", "answer": "Hurricane <b><u>Katrina</u> </b> [Joe Nutter]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A work by this man inspired al-Farabi\u2019s [ahl fuh-RAH-bee\u2019s] book <em>The Virtuous City</em>. In one of this man\u2019s works, the title character offers to break his friend out of prison, but is stopped by that friend's insistence on following the law. One of this man's works presents four \u201caffections\u201d of the psyche using the Analogy of the Divided Line. In that work, this man conceived of a perfect state ruled by philosopher-kings. For 10 points, name this author of the <em>Crito</em> and <em>Republic</em>, two of his namesake dialogues.", "answer": "<b><u>Plato</u></b> [or <b><u>Platon</u></b>]  [Chris Man<u>ners]</u>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "One of this king\u2019s cabinet ministers was wounded at Putney Heath after a duel. He was advised early in life by Lord Bute and married Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz [STRAYE-Lits]. After this man refused to support Catholic Emancipation, his prime minister Pitt the Younger resigned. Earlier in his reign, Pitt the Elder helped this king defeat France and Lord North passed the Intolerable Acts. For 10 points, name this mad king who ruled during the American Revolution.", "answer": "King <b><u>George III</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>George</u></b>]  [Laurence Li]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The English chemist John Mayow predicted the existence of this element upon observing that antimony increased in weight when heated. This element reacted to produce banded-iron formations before its rise in atmospheric abundance. It was discovered independently by Carl Wilhelm Scheele in 1773 and later by Joseph Priestley in 1774. For 10 points, name this element whose diatomic form is \u201cdephlogisticated\u201d air, the second-most abundant atmospheric gas.", "answer": "<b><u>oxygen</u></b> [or <b><u>O</u></b>]  [Sriram Pen<u>dyala]</u>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "The Qaynuqa [kay-NOOK-uh] were expelled from this city after a jeweler began a feud by inadvertently stripping off a woman's dress. This city\u2019s warring factions, the Khazraj [KOZZ-razh] and Aus [OWS], made peace in its namesake Constitution, which granted full protection to Christians and Jews. This city also known as Yathrib [yuh-THREEB] defended itself at the Battle of the Trench from the neighboring Quraysh [koo-RYESH] tribe, who pursued a man who fled here in 622 CE during the Hijra. For 10 points, name this Arabian city in the Hejaz [hih-JOZZ], the second holiest in Islam after Mecca.", "answer": "<b><u>Medina</u> </b> [Chris Ray]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A character in a Mark Twain novel describes this sport as \u201cpicturesque and ridiculous.\u201d This sport\u2019s name is derived from the Latin word meaning \u201cto approach\u201d or \u201cto meet.\u201d The French Wars of Religion were partially triggered by Henry II\u2019s death from this activity. The equipment used by later participants in this sport helped spread the myth that medieval armor was hard to move in. For 10 points, name this sport in which knights on horseback attempt to unseat one another, typically with a lance.", "answer": "<b><u>joust</u></b>ing [or <b><u>tilt</u></b>ing; or word forms; prompt on participating in <b><u>tournament</u></b>s and <b><u>tourney</u></b>s]  <u>[Blake N</u>eff]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The early Christian thinker Tertullian [turr-TOOL-ee-uhn] asked \u201cwhat has (this city) to do with Jerusalem?\u201d The royal stoa [STOH-uh] of Attalos [uh-TALL-ohs] is found in this city.  Berlin\u2019s Brandenburg Gate was copied from a large gate to a landmark in this city called the Propylaea [pro-pull-AYE-uh]. The explosion of an Ottoman munitions dump damaged this city's most famous landmark, from which a set of marble sculptures were removed by Lord Elgin. For 10 points, name this European capital city in which the Parthenon [PAR-thuh-nonn] can be found on the Acropolis [uh-CROP-uh-luhs].", "answer": "<b><u>Athens</u></b> [or <b><u>Athina</u></b>; or <b><u>Athenai</u></b>]  [Doug Grae<u>bner]</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This man delivered a speech that calls for \u201cscorching irony,\u201d in which the answer to the title question is \u201ca day that reveals gross injustice and cruelty.\u201d This author of \u201cWhat to The Slave is  The Fourth of July?\u201d lived at Cedar Hill and clashed with William Lloyd Garrison. This man fled Talbot County and wrote an autobiographical work describing learning to read in the sand. For 10 points, name this author of <em>My Bondage and My Freedom,</em> a famous escaped slave and abolitionist.", "answer": "Frederick <b><u>Douglass</u></b> [or Frederick Augustus Washington <b><u>Bailey</u></b>]  [Douglas Graebner]", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This son of Saint Sylvia was described by John Calvin as the last good pope. This man was  the first monk to become pope, and adopted the title \u201cServant of the servants of God\u201d to contrast with the Eastern title of Ecumenical [ECK-yoo-MEN-ih-cull] Patriarch. This man is credited with sending the papal mission that evangelized the pagan Anglo-Saxons of post-Roman Britain. For 10 points, name this pope who is the namesake of a type of monastic chant.", "answer": "Pope <b><u>Gregory</u></b> the <b><u>Great</u></b> [or <b><u>Gregory I</u></b>; or <b><u>Gregorius I</u></b>; prompt on partial answer] [Blake Neff]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In one book, this man proposed that Moses was a relative of the Egyptian Akhenaten. This man investigated views of incest among the Aborigines in the first section of his book <em>Totem and</em> <em>Taboo</em>. This man conceived of the \"death drive\" in a book attributing human behavior to sexual drive. For 10 points, name this psychologist who conceived of the Oedipus complex and founded psychoanalysis.", "answer": "Sigmund <b>Freud</b> [FROYD] [or Sigismund Schlomo <b>Freud</b>]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "In Israel, the Ale Yarok party is best known for its platform on this substance. Rick Steves argued that many current laws about this substance affect \u201cpeople who are arrested and cited, who are poor,\u201d not \u201crich white guys\u201d who enjoy it. The U.S. House of Representatives passed a 2014 bill that prevented welfare funds going to states that defy the FDA and DEA and have legalized this substance. For 10 points, name this plant-based drug now legal in DC, Washington, and Colorado.", "answer": "<b>marijuana</b> [or <b>cannabis</b>, <b>weed</b>, <b>pot</b>, <b>grass</b> etc.]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This person, who was hired after her critical response to the \u201cQuiet Observer\u201d column in the Pittsburgh Dispatch won admirers, once spent 10 days undercover at Blackwell\u2019s Island in order to expose the cruel treatment of the mentally ill. She took her pen name from a Stephen Foster song and her most well-known feat involved traveling by burro, train and ship. For 10 points, name this \u201cstunt reporter\u201d who completed a 72-day round-the-world trip in 1889.", "answer": "Nellie <b>Bly</b> [or Elizabeth Jane <b>Cochran</b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A document written by this man was ordered revoked by Francis Bernard. This man was succeeded by Increase Sumner in one position, and this author of the Circular Letter often met at the Old South Meeting House. This Massachusetts resident helped organize the Boston Tea Party. For 10 points, name this American revolutionary who was the cousin of the 2nd President.", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Adams</u></b> [or Sam <b><u>Adams</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This movement was satirically criticized in the newspaper <em>Le Charivari</em> [lay sharr-uh-varr-ee] by Louis Leroy [loo-ee luh-roy] and took its name from a painting of the harbor of Le Havre [lay hahv] over which the sun rises. The Salon of the Refused often exhibited this movement\u2019s works, including <em>Luncheon on the Grass</em>. For 10 points, name this art movement whose members included Pierre-Auguste Renoir and Claude Monet.", "answer": "<b><u>Impression</u></b>ism [accept word forms]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler repressed the \u201cpride and folly\u201d of Tassilo, the rebellious Duke of Bavaria, and fought battles against the Avars that rendered Pannonia [pann-OH-nee-uh] an uninhabitable wasteland. His court at Aachen [OCK-en] was the center of a domain that he passed on to his son, Louis the Pious. For 10 points, name this Frankish king, a patron of learning who became the first Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u></b> [or <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; or <b><u>Carolus Magnus;</u></b> or <b><u>Karl der Grosse</u></b>]  T<u>he two major li</u>ves <u>of Charlemagne we</u>re w<u>ritten by Notker [</u>NO<u>T-kurr] the</u> Stammerer and what courtier [COURT-eer] who studied at Charlemagne\u2019s palace school? ANSWER: <b><u>Einhard</u></b> [INE-hard]  [Jeff Hoppe<u>s]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This scientist\u2019s father developed achromatic lenses to perfect the optical microscope. He  himself came out of retirement to consult on the treatment of Edward VII\u2019s appendicitis. Most famously, he applied lint soaked in carbolic acid to a boy\u2019s wound and found that after four days, no infection had occurred. For 10 points, name this surgeon who pioneered the use of antiseptics in surgery.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Lister</u> </b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "In this war, the French captured Minorca [min-OR-cuh], which was returned at its end.  Saltykov [SALT-yuh-koff] and Loudon [loo-dohn] dealt a heavy loss to the Prussians at Kunersdorf [KOON-urs-dorf] in this war in which Rossbach [ROSS-bock] and Leuthen [LOY-tunn] were sites of victories by Frederick the Great. Canada became a British colony after the Treaty of Paris that ended this war. For 10 points, name this worldwide war that lasted from 1756 to 1763.", "answer": "<b><u>Seven Years</u></b>\u2019 War [or <b><u>French and Indian</u></b> War; or <b><u>Third Carnatic</u></b> War]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A composer from this country adapted his</u> </b><em><b><u>Lachrimae pavane</u></b></em><b><u> [LACK-ree-may puh-</u><u>V</u><u>ONN] into the lute song \u201cFlow my tears.\u201d Another composer from this country was</u></b> <b><u>inspired by the horrors of World War I to write an E minor (+)</u><u> cello concerto that w</u>as <u>popularized by Jacqueline du Pre [zhock-uh-leen doo pray]. Th</u>at composer from thsi country depicted Augustus Jaeger [YAY-gurr] in the \u201cNimrod\u201d movement of his (*) </b><em>Enigma Variations</em> and wrote six <em>Pomp and Circumstance</em> marches often heard at graduations. For 10 points, name this country, the home of John Dowland and Edward Elgar.", "answer": "<b><u>England</u></b> [or the <b><u>United Kingdom</u></b> of Great Britain and Northern Ireland; or Great <b><u>Britain</u></b>; or <u>the</u> <b><u>UK</u></b><u>]</u>  <u>[Eddie</u> Kim]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man names a theorem presented in Book XIII [\u201ceight\u201d] of Euclid\u2019s Elements that</u></b> <b><u>re</u><u>lates the products of diagonal lengths for a cyclic quadrilateral to products of side</u></b> <b><u>lengths. He also names a (+)</u><u> list of ancient kings and their chronology that orders ru</u>lers <u>between the Babylonian em</u>pire and the Roman empire. This man added a \u201ccrank mechanism\u201d to Hipparchus\u2019 notions of (*)</b> deferent and epicycle. For 10 points, name this Alexandrian polymath who names the geocentric model of the universe, and who wrote the <em>Almagest</em> [ALL-muh-jest].", "answer": "<b><u>Ptolemy</u></b> [or Claudius <b><u>Ptolemy</u></b>]  [Sriram Pen<u>dyala]</u>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>This conflict was called a \u201cwar without an enemy\u201d by William Waller, who spent most of</u></b> <b><u>it</u> <u>fighting against Hopton's Cornish army. Incidents in this war included the Battle of</u></b> <b><u>Chalgrove Field, where John Hampden was fatally wounded, and the defense of Turn</u><u>ham</u></b> <b><u>Green by the trained bands of</u><u> (+) London. This war's outcome was decided at the Battle o</u>f Naseby, where the \u201cOxford Army\u201d was smashed by the (*)</b> Roundhead cavalry of the New Model Army. For 10 points, name this 17th century conflict in which the Long Parliament defeated Stuart royalists.", "answer": "First <b><u>English Civil</u></b> War  [Jeff Hoppes]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A riot targeting a certain group in this state began in the \u201cSand Lot\u201d and was put down</u></b> <b><u>by</u><u> the Pick Handle Brigade. This state was home to outlaws like Red-Handed Dick and</u></b> <b><u>Joaquin Murietta [wah-KEEN moor-ee-AY-tuh]. The Workingman\u2019s (+)</u><u> Party in this s</u>tate <u>was led by Denis Kearney. The owner of the Central Pacific Railroad bec</u>ame governor of this state in the 1860s. An influx of (*)</b> immigration led this state to pass laws limiting the rights of Chinese to hold property. For 10 points, name this western U.S. state, admitted to the Union after its Gold Rush of 1849.", "answer": "State of <b><u>California</u> </b> [Naveed Chowdhur<u>y- ed. Dan</u> Puma]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's staff secretary was Andrew Goodpaster. This president denied IMF</u></b> <b><u>as</u><u>sistance to one country to help halt Operation Musketeer. During this man\u2019s pr</u><u>esidency,</u></b> <b><u>the CIA overthrew</u> <u>(+)</u><u>Mohammed Mossadegh in Iran and Jacobo Arbenz [yuh-KOH-boh</u></b> <b><u>ARR-benz] in Guat</u>emala. This president\u2019s Secretary of State, who coined the term \u201cbrinkmanship,\u201dwas (*)</b> John Foster Dulles. This man signed the interstate highway act and ended the Korean War. For 10 points, name this former Allied commander and president during the 1950's.", "answer": "Dwight D. <b><u>Eisenhower</u></b> [or Dwight David <b><u>Eisenhower</u></b>; or <b><u>Ike</u></b>]  [Laurence Li]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This song\u2019s music video, which depicts the newspaper headline \u201cELVIS JOINS THE</u></b> <b><u>A</u><u>RMY,\u201d is set in a suburban American household. This song\u2019s mention of</u><u> (+)</u> </b><em><b><u>Psycho</u></b></em><b><u> is</u></b> <b><u>accompanied by the signature violin screeches from that film. This song op</u>ens with the line \u201cHarry Truman, Doris Day, (*) </b>Red China, Johnnie Ray,\u201d while its chorus notes that the title phenomenon \u201cwas always burning since the world\u2019s been turning.\u201d For 10 points, name this song by Billy Joel that lists various historical events.", "answer": "\"<b><u>We Didn't Start the Fire</u></b>\"  [Kenji Golim<u>lim]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This project was originally named BONIFACE to give the illusion that a well-placed spy</u></b> <b><u>wa</u><u>s responsible for the project. The addition of a fourth (+)</u><u> rotor was a major setback for</u> <u>this project. Under this project, Gordon Welchman invente</u>d the bombe [\u201cbomb\u201d] at Bletchley Park with the help of (*) </b>Alan Turing, and its success meant accurate tracking of U-boat movements. For 10 points, identify this project which allowed the Allies to read Axis encrypted communications by deciphering a certain machine.", "answer": "codebreaking the <b><u>Enigma</u></b> machine [or <b><u>Ultra</u></b>, or any answer mentioning breaking <b><u>Enigma</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Bletchle</u><u>y Park</u></b><u> b</u>efore it is rea<u>d]</u>  <u>[Victor</u> Prieto]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In response to a rebellion sparked by one of these events, Narses distributed gold to its</u></b> <b><u>sp</u><u>ectators. Participants in these events used the</u> </b><em><b><u>biga</u></b></em><b><u> [BEE-guh] or the</u> </b><em><b><u>quadriga</u></b></em><b><u> [quod-</u><u>REEG-uh]. An uprising that started during one of these events sought to crown (+)</u></b> <b><u>Hypatius as the new emperor. These events, which were attended by groups such a</u>s the Blues, Greens, and Whites, were the origin of the Nika [NEEK-uh] Riots against (*) </b>Justinian. They were held at the Hippodrome in Constantinople and the Circus Maximus in Rome. For 10 points, name these contests that involved carts pulled by horses.", "answer": "Roman <b><u>chariot race</u></b>s [or Byzantine <b><u>chariot race</u></b>s; prompt on partial answer] [Kenji Golimlim]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}